43 chapter 44 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 44 Old Captain and His
Successor Captain and I I were great friends. He was a noble old fellow, and he
was very good company. I never thought that he would have to leave his home and
go down the hill; but his turn came, and this was how it happened. I was not there,
but I heard all about it. He and Jerry had taken a party to the
great railway station over London Bridge, and were coming back, somewhere between
the bridge and the monument, when Jerry saw a brewer's empty Dre coming along,
drawn by two powerful horses. The Dre was lashing his horses with his heavy whip;
the Dre was light, and they started off at a furious rate; the man had no control
over them, and the street was full of traffic. One young girl was knocked down
and run over, and the next moment they dashed up against our cab; both the
wheels were torn off and the cab was thrown over. Captain was dragged down, the shafts
splintered, and one of them ran into his side. Jerry, too, was thrown, but was only
bruised; nobody could tell how he escaped; he always said it was a
miracle. When poor Captain was got up he was found to be very much cut and knocked
about. Jerry led him home gently, and a sad sight it was to see the blood
soaking into his white coat and dropping from his side and
shoulder. The Draymond was proved to be very drunk, and was fined, and the brewer
had to pay damages to our master; but there was no one to pay damages to poor
Captain. The farer and and Jerry did the best they could to ease his pain and
make him comfortable. The fly had to be mended, and for several days I did not go
out, and Jerry earned nothing. The first time we went to the
stand after the accident the governor came up to hear how Captain was HEK
never get over it,” said Jerry, “at least not for my work, so the fer said this
morning. He says he may do for carting, and that sort of work. It has put me out
very much. Carting, indeed! I've seen what horses come to at that work around
London. I knew wish all the drunkards could be put in a lunatic asylum instead
of being allowed to run foul of sober people. If they would break their own
bones, and smash their own carts, and lame their own horses, that would be their own
affair, and we might let them alone, but it seems to me that the innocent always
suffer; and then they talk about compensation! You can't make compensation;
there's all the trouble, and vexation, and loss of time, besides losing a good horse
that's like an old friend— —it's nonsense talking of compensation! If there's one
devil that I should like to see in the bottomless pit more than another, it's the drink
devil.” “I say, Jerry,” said the governor, “you were treading pretty hard on my toes, you
know; I'm not so good as you are, more shame to me; I wish I
was.” “Well,” said Jerry, “why don't you cut with it, governor? You are too good a man
to be the slave of such a thing.” “I'm a great fool, Jerry, but I tried
once for two days, and I I thought I should have died; how did you
do?” “I had hard work at it for several weeks; you see I never did get drunk, but
I found that I was not my own master, and that when the craving came on it was
hard work to say 'no'. I saw that one of us must knock under, the drink devil or
Jerry Barker, and I said that it should not be Jerry Barker, God helping me; but
it was a struggle, and I wanted all the help I could get, for till I tried to
break the habit I did not know how strong it was; but then Polly took such
pains that I should have good food, and when the craving came on I used to get a
cup of coffee, or some peppermint, or read
a bit in my book, and that was a help to
me; sometimes I had to say over and over to myself, 'Give up the drink or lose your
soul! Give up the drink or break Polly's heart!' But thanks be to God, and my dear
wife, my chains were broken, and now for 10 years I have not tasted a drop, and
never wish for it.” “I've a great mind to try at it,” said
Grant, “for it is a poor thing not to be one's own master.” “Do, governor, do, you'll never
repent it, and what a help it would be to
some of the poor fellows in our rank if they saw you do without it. I know
there's two or three would like to keep out of that tavern if they
could.” At first Captain seemed to do well, but he was a very old horse, and it was
only his wonderful constitution, and Jerry's care, that had kept him up at the
cab work so long; now he broke down very much. The farer said he might mend up
enough to sell for a few pounds, but Jerry said, no! a few pounds got by
selling a good old servant into hard work and misery would caner all the rest
of his money, and he thought the kindest thing he could do for the fine old
fellow would be to put a sh bullet through his head, and then he would never
suffer more; for he did not know where to find a kind master for the rest of his
days. The day after this was decided Harry took me to the forge for some new shoes;
when I returned Captain was gone. I and the family all felt it very
much. Jerry had now to look out for another horse, and he soon heard of one
through an acquaintance who was underg Grom in a nobleman's
stables. He was a valuable young horse, but he had run away, smashed into another
carriage, flung his lordship out, and so cut and blemished himself that he was no
longer fit for a gentleman's stables, and the coachman had orders to look around
and sell him as well as he could. “I can do with high spirits,” said
Jerry, “if a horse is not vicious or hard
mouthed There is not a bit of ice in him,” said the man; “his mouth is very tender,
and I think myself that was the cause of the accident; you see he had just been
clipped, and the weather was bad, and he had not had exercise enough, and when he
did go out he was as full of spring as a balloon. Our governor (the coachman, I mean)
had him harnessed in as tight and strong as he could, with the marting Gale and
the check rain a very sharp curb, and the
rains put in at the bottom bar. It is my belief that it made the horse mad, being
tender in the mouth and so full of spirit.” “Likely enough; I'll come and see him,” said
Jerry. The next day Hotspur, that was his name, came home; he was a fine brown horse,
without a white hair in him, as tall as Captain, with a very handsome head, and
only five years old. I gave him a friendly greeting by
way of good fellowship, but did not ask him any questions. The first night he was very
restless. Instead of lying down, he kept jerking his halter rope up and down
through the ring, and knocking the block about against the manger till I could not
sleep. However, the next day, after five or six hours in the cab, he came in quiet
and sensible. Jerry patted and talked to him a good deal, and very soon they
understood each other, and Jerry said that with an easy bit and plenty of work
he would be as gentle as a lamb; and that
it was an ill wind that blew nobody good, for if his lordship had lost a 100 gine
favorite, the cabman had gained a good horse with all his strength in
him. Hotspur thought it a great come down to be a cab horse and was disgusted at
standing in the rank, but he confessed to me at the end of the week that an easy
mouth and a free head made up for a great deal, and after all, the work was
not so degrading as having one's head and tail fastened to each other at the
saddle. In fact, he settled in well, and Jerry liked him very much End of chapter